<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-03T21:30:57-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">On Knowing</title><subtitle>The practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is Knowledge?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Knowledge?" /><published>2022-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge/"><![CDATA[<p>Many people think very naively about knowing something. Their will state knowlegde is a belief which is true. 
A typical example of something people claim to know is that the sun will rise in the morning. The predictive nature of this statement comes under
immediate attack as failing to be true after a supernova.</p>

<p>Even when the statement is narrowed to the sun came up this morning, and I know this because I saw it. Many other questions such as where you 
were located come into play. Requiring all knowledge to be the result of personal experience is very limiting. Moreover, the experiments bringing into
question the accuracy of eyewitnesses can shack peoples faith in the ability of anyone to know anything.</p>

<p>Part of the problem lies in requiring knowledge to be always true. Newtonian mechanics made way for the theory of relativity. Yet today Newton’s theory is
still taught as knowledge with the caveat that it works except in unusual situations such as moving very close to the speed of light.</p>

<p>The simplest definition of knowledge is a believe with evidence demostrating it is true.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many people think very naively about knowing something. Their will state knowlegde is a belief which is true. A typical example of something people claim to know is that the sun will rise in the morning. The predictive nature of this statement comes under immediate attack as failing to be true after a supernova.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Night-Owl.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Night-Owl.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to On Knowing!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to On Knowing!" /><published>2022-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing/"><![CDATA[<p>On Knowing is the blog for <a href="https://www.researchonknowing.com/">Research on Knowing LLC</a>. Here you will find articles posted exploring 
the practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.</p>

<p>Epistemology within Philosophy is “the theory of knowledge, especially with regard to its methods, validity, and scope. 
Epistemology is the investigation of what distinguishes justified belief from opinion.” (OxfordLanguages) 
Make sure to read the theory articles first for a basic foundation on our philosophy of knowledge.
Other posts will expand on this foundation diving deeper into the details.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, various other Research on Knowing projects apply our philosophy of knowledge. We at Research on Knowing believe the practical 
application of epistemology can open our eyes and change our point of view. 
The invention of the telescope changed humanities ideas and understanding of the stars and planets. 
The microscope made visible an unimagined world within a drop of water. 
These are examples of how making visible what was previously hidden has revolutionized our knowledge. 
Computers and software have expanded our knowledge by revealing unseen truths. 
Research on Knowing employs these kinds of changes in viewpoint to explore how we learn, understand and create things.</p>

<p>Thank you for joining us on this journey. We hope your discovers here at On Knowing will be enlightening.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Knowing is the blog for Research on Knowing LLC. Here you will find articles posted exploring the practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Night-Owl-in-Flight.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Night-Owl-in-Flight.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>