<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-07T20:12:24-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">On Knowing</title><subtitle>The practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Beyond Fundamentalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/beyond-fundamentalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Fundamentalism" /><published>2022-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/beyond-fundamentalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/beyond-fundamentalism/"><![CDATA[<p>Religious conservatives have given fundamentalism a bad reputation. “Epistemology of Descartes is known as Fundamentalism. In his book of 
Meditations on First Philosophy, Descartes tries to find some basis of knowledge. He is searching for total certainty, and by doing so, he subjects 
everything to doubt. Through it comes to the only thing he thinks he has the certainty of, his existence.” (UKEssays, 2018) 
Descartes’ approach has been used to describe mathematical systems and some scientific theories. First principles are adopted as true 
from which everything else is logically proven or demonstrated. Euclidian Geometry is often cited as an example.</p>

<p>Christian Fundamentalists motivated by a desire for absolute certainty have adopted a list of tenets they hold as unquestionably true. 
One such tenet is the Christian Bible is inerrant. Here everything written in the Bible is believed
to be the word of God and therefore must be taken as true. The position runs into trouble when the logical inconsistencies within scripture are 
pointed out. Christian Fundamentalists have to engage in a significant amount of mental gymnastics attempting to rationalize these 
inconsistencies away.</p>

<p>Abandoning the requirement for absolute certainty allows us to escape and move beyond fundamentalism. First principles can be viewed pragmatically 
as useful starting points for creating a system. The first principles can be seen as approximations rather than absolute truths. Geometry assumes 
space is continuous and infinitely divisible. Physical space-time may actually be digital. The results in geometry, however, can still approximate 
the same outcomes whether space-time is infinitely divisible or digital. This is because the resolution of our physical universe is so high that 
discrepancies become the two models are indistinguishable to human perception. Similarly, as the resolution increases, digital music recordings are 
superior to their analog equivalents particularly because analog records contain noise which is eliminated through digital representation.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-begin">Where to Begin</h2>

<p>In selecting a set of principles to create a system the essential characteristics are as follows:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Each principle should a single, simple item rather than a compound collection of ideas.</li>
  <li>The principles should be independent. The validity of any one principle should not affectthe validity of the other principles.</li>
  <li>The principles should be essential with no principles being derived from the other principles.</li>
  <li>The principles should be necessary where removing a principle reduces the set of provablemembers within the system.
The principles generate a system through logical reasoning.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="loops">Loops</h2>

<p>Some systems may be possible to 
construct using different sets of first principles. The reinforcing circulator logic for these 
systems yields a loop architecture. The loop is like the question, “What came first, the chicken or the egg?” 
Structures with this circulator and self-referential quality are detailed by Douglas Hofstadter in his books—Gödel, Escher, Bach (Hofstadter, 1979) 
and I Am a Strange Loop (Hofstadter, 2007).</p>

<h3 id="references">References:</h3>

<p>Hofstadter, D. R. (1999). <em>Gödel, Escher, Bach: An eternal golden braid</em>. Basic Books.</p>

<p>Hofstadter, D. R. (2007). <em>I Am a Strange Loop</em>. Basic Books.</p>

<p>UKEssays. (November 2018). Descartes Epistemology Known As Fundamentalism Philosophy Essay. 
Retrieved from 
<a href="https://www.ukessays.com/essays/philosophy/descartes-epistemology-known-as-fundamentalism-philosophy-essay.php?vref=1">https://www.ukessays.com/essays/philosophy/descartes-epistemology-known-as-fundamentalism-philosophy-essay.php?vref=1</a></p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Religious conservatives have given fundamentalism a bad reputation. “Epistemology of Descartes is known as Fundamentalism. In his book of Meditations on First Philosophy, Descartes tries to find some basis of knowledge. He is searching for total certainty, and by doing so, he subjects everything to doubt. Through it comes to the only thing he thinks he has the certainty of, his existence.” (UKEssays, 2018) Descartes’ approach has been used to describe mathematical systems and some scientific theories. First principles are adopted as true from which everything else is logically proven or demonstrated. Euclidian Geometry is often cited as an example.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/61/Mandelbrot_Budding_turbines.jpg/640px-Mandelbrot_Budding_turbines.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/61/Mandelbrot_Budding_turbines.jpg/640px-Mandelbrot_Budding_turbines.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating Everyone Everywhere Affordable Broadband Access</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Creating-Everyone-Everywhere-Affordable-Broadband-Access/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating Everyone Everywhere Affordable Broadband Access" /><published>2022-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Creating-Everyone-Everywhere-Affordable-Broadband-Access</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Creating-Everyone-Everywhere-Affordable-Broadband-Access/"><![CDATA[<p>We produced a paper with recommendations for creating affordable fiber optic
broadband access. Below is the executive summary, and here is the 
<a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zAyzFysyT33g34YLvkvh9l4Kwj32kaBC/view?usp=sharing">full paper</a></p>

<h2 id="executive-summary">Executive Summary</h2>

<p>This paper provides essential recommendations for creating affordable fiber optic
broadband access. The current goal for service is 100 Mbps symmetrical (download
and upload speed) at no more than $70/month. By 2032, 1 Gbps should be available
for $100/month. Fiber optic technology should be used and the resulting network
infrastructure should be publicly owned and regulated. Neighborhood networking
projects decompose the larger network allowing the pursuit of a divide and conquer
strategy. Each neighborhood project is driven by local support which can be financed
as Local Utility Districts (LUD), grants, or other funding sources. A menu of private
Internet Service Provider (ISP) companies compete to provide end-user services. Tools
and other considerations that support effective implementation include online network
performance testing and mapping to direct network implementation, cost-benefit
analysis using total cost of operation for decisions such as underground versus aerial
fiber optic installation, and implementation of a dig once policy to accelerate network
backbone growth while saving both time and money. Dig once needs proper incentives
to reward compliance.</p>]]></content><author><name>dan</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We produced a paper with recommendations for creating affordable fiber optic broadband access. Below is the executive summary, and here is the full paper]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c1/Fiber_optic2.jpg/512px-Fiber_optic2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c1/Fiber_optic2.jpg/512px-Fiber_optic2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning from Mistakes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning-from-mistakes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning from Mistakes" /><published>2022-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning-from-mistakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning-from-mistakes/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iuE_a1pTsO4">‘Frog and Peach’</a> comedy routine features Dudley Moore interviewing an eccentric restaurant owner 
played by Peter Cook. Cook describes in detail a failed restaurant that only serves a large frog with a peach in its mouth or a peach sliced open 
with tadpoles swimming in the area where the peach pit would be. When ask why the business failed Cook responds that he believes it had something 
to do with the menu. The punchline occurs when Dudley Moore asks, “But you’ve learned from your mistakes.” Peter Cook responds emphatically, 
“Yes! I can repeat them exactly.”</p>

<p>Knowing why a failure has occurred and what actions would have succeeded in avoiding the errors turns out to be more challenging than people 
often realize. The process of discovering the successful course of action is usually trial and error. Only when an attempt using the corrected 
approach has succeeded can you confirm you learned from the mistake.</p>

<p>Even when situations work out the way we want, it’s easy to mistakenly believe our actions are responsible for success. The causality between our 
actions and the outcomes may be incorrect. The outcome may have occurred no matter what actions we employ. Careful analysis and verification that 
a particular situation is fully understood can improve our chances of actually learning from a mistake rather than compounding our error 
by learning the wrong lesson.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ‘Frog and Peach’ comedy routine features Dudley Moore interviewing an eccentric restaurant owner played by Peter Cook. Cook describes in detail a failed restaurant that only serves a large frog with a peach in its mouth or a peach sliced open with tadpoles swimming in the area where the peach pit would be. When ask why the business failed Cook responds that he believes it had something to do with the menu. The punchline occurs when Dudley Moore asks, “But you’ve learned from your mistakes.” Peter Cook responds emphatically, “Yes! I can repeat them exactly.”]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/learn-from-mistakes.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/learn-from-mistakes.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trial &amp;amp; Error vs Recipe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/trial-n-error-vs-recipe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trial &amp;amp; Error vs Recipe" /><published>2022-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/trial-n-error-vs-recipe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/trial-n-error-vs-recipe/"><![CDATA[<p>Problem-solving can be seen broadly as transitioning a situation from one state to another. This view covers a host of human endeavors. 
Most often the end state is considered a goal or objective. Problem-solving methods can be categorized as either trial and error or 
the use of a recipe. Recipe implies a method with a proven track record for success. Trial and error, however, attempts an approach 
that hasn’t been done successfully. The task of baking oatmeal raisin cookies can be done through trial and error 
where various ingredients are combined. You might expect that through careful experimentation a batch of oatmeal raisin cookies 
that are suitable for consumption might result. But you would also expect in the process to produce several batches of either soggy mush or 
inedible bricks.</p>

<p>By following a recipe for oatmeal cookies, it’s possible to produce an excellent batch on your first attempt. 
The key lesson here is to use a recipe whenever you can. Recipes have originated through trial and error experimentation. 
Using a recipe benefits from the experience, lessons learned, and discoveries of others. A recipe allows you to avoid repeating 
the mistakes others have encountered and save both time and money.</p>

<p>When no recipe exists to do exactly what you want starting with the recipe closest to the goal and applying a trial and error to modify 
it is an excellent approach. You are essentially starting further along the learning curve to create a recipe that meets your requirements. 
Adding some chopped macadamia nuts to your oatmeal raisin cookie recipe is one example. This particular modification may be unusual and 
not guaranteed to be to your liking. Beginning with a recipe to attempt this combination still avoids a lot of unnecessary mistakes.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Problem-solving can be seen broadly as transitioning a situation from one state to another. This view covers a host of human endeavors. Most often the end state is considered a goal or objective. Problem-solving methods can be categorized as either trial and error or the use of a recipe. Recipe implies a method with a proven track record for success. Trial and error, however, attempts an approach that hasn’t been done successfully. The task of baking oatmeal raisin cookies can be done through trial and error where various ingredients are combined. You might expect that through careful experimentation a batch of oatmeal raisin cookies that are suitable for consumption might result. But you would also expect in the process to produce several batches of either soggy mush or inedible bricks.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/09/Oatmeal_Cookies_with_orange_zest%2C_golden_raisins%2C_and_chocolate_chips.jpg/512px-Oatmeal_Cookies_with_orange_zest%2C_golden_raisins%2C_and_chocolate_chips.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/09/Oatmeal_Cookies_with_orange_zest%2C_golden_raisins%2C_and_chocolate_chips.jpg/512px-Oatmeal_Cookies_with_orange_zest%2C_golden_raisins%2C_and_chocolate_chips.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Math Works</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-math-works/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Math Works" /><published>2022-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-math-works</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-math-works/"><![CDATA[<p>Math stands alone in the discussions of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM). 
Other fields of endeavor rely upon mathematics to create models of theories and work products. 
The usefulness of mathematics comes from being inspired by physical reality without relying upon it. 
Like Aristotle described the teachings of Socrates where reality is a shadow of a perfect idealized existence, 
math looks at a system where a few postulates are taken to be true. Assuming a method of logical reasoning, 
mathematicians prove a host of theorems all based on the assumed truth of these postulates or axioms.</p>

<p>Euclidean geometry illustrates the essential mathematical approach. Euclid formulated five postulates as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>A straight line segment can be drawn joining any two points.</li>
  <li>Any straight line segment can be extended indefinitely in a straight line.</li>
  <li>Given any straight line segment, a circle can be drawn having the segment as radius and one endpoint as center.</li>
  <li>All right angles are congruent.</li>
  <li>If two lines are drawn which intersect a third in such a way that the sum of the inner angles on one side is less than two right angles, 
then the two lines inevitably must intersect each other on that side if extended far enough. 
This postulate is equivalent to what is known as the parallel postulate. (“Euclid’s Postulates”, 2022)</li>
</ol>

<p>A point in Euclid’s geometry, does not have any dimension. It has no width or length and breadth unlike any point you might draw in the real world.
Straight lines only have length and extend infinitely. While, there is no evidence points and lines behave this way in the physical world, 
mathematics does not require any such verification. There are no experiments which can be conducted to invalidate the theorems of geometry. 
If you accept the axioms then everything else in geometry is proved using the methods of logical reasoning.</p>

<p>Non-Euclidean geometry drops the 5th postulate allowing parallel lines to intersect. 
The new geometry creates an alternative mathematical system which has been used successfully to model 
such things as the geometry of objects on the surface of a sphere.</p>

<p>Physics moved past the three dimensional model of space from Euclidean geometry. Current models include time as a four dimensional manifold. 
Some theories add even further dimensions. Even the continuous nature of space has been questioned. 
It’s possible that our universe is actually digital although the resolution is extremely high.</p>

<p>In work where the axioms of Euclidean geometry are accepted, the mathematical models created put the emphasis on examining 
the validity of the models within the field of endeavor.
Isaac Newton created both a system of mechanics for physics and the mathematics of calculus. 
Calculus was used to model the laws of motion within mechanics. Once the theorems of calculus were proved, the models for mechanics 
using the new math of calculus produced predictions which could be tested in experiments. Some models where shown 
inaccurate failing to describe  how motion actually works. While, double checking for a math errors is reasonable, 
the validity of calculus itself remained solidly intact. Giving confidence to the researcher’s investigation of these natural phenomenon. 
Again, the focus remains on the science and not the mathematics.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<p>Euclid’s Postulates. (2022). Retrieved August 2, 2022, from Wolfram.com website: 
<a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/EuclidsPostulates.html">https://mathworld.wolfram.com/EuclidsPostulates.html</a></p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Math stands alone in the discussions of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM). Other fields of endeavor rely upon mathematics to create models of theories and work products. The usefulness of mathematics comes from being inspired by physical reality without relying upon it. Like Aristotle described the teachings of Socrates where reality is a shadow of a perfect idealized existence, math looks at a system where a few postulates are taken to be true. Assuming a method of logical reasoning, mathematicians prove a host of theorems all based on the assumed truth of these postulates or axioms.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/whiteboard-math.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/whiteboard-math.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Experience of Reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/experience-of-reality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experience of Reality" /><published>2022-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/experience-of-reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/experience-of-reality/"><![CDATA[<p>In the movie <em>The Matrix</em> (1999) the scene <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VVro5wxqh4U">What is Real?</a> has the main character named Neo connected 
to a computer simulation with a terminal jack in the back of his head. Once in the simulation Neo questions the nature of his reality. The 
discussion puts forth a model of human perception where energy signals such as light, sound, heat, and chemicals impinge on the sensory receptors in 
the human body. The receptors react sending impulses through the nervous system to the brain. The brain interprets these impulses constructing a 
mental model creating an individual’s experience of the world around them as what they see, hear, feel, smell, and taste. Our sensory system only 
samples a small amount of the energy fields and chemical molecules present in the environment directly around us. Our brains interpolate to fill any 
gaps where data is missing. The sensory processing system can be thought of as our input from the physical world we live in.</p>

<p>The reciprocal output is where the brain and nervous system send impulses to effectors to cause the body to carry on any actions such flex a muscle, 
blinking eyes, or vocal cord action to speak. Many bodily functions occur automatically through the anatomic nervous system. Others operate under 
conscious control by the individual. Although, individuals often overestimate (and sometimes underestimate) how much actual conscious control they 
exert over their bodily functions.</p>

<p>The fascinating question posed in <em>The Matrix</em> movie is how would you know the difference between signals supplied to your nervous system from a 
computer simulation and those from the “real world”?</p>

<p>An important psychological phenomenon to understand is filtering. Our experience is netted together from data sampling within our environment. Past 
experience and our belief system have a profound effect on our experience of reality. We make predictions and fill in gaps guided by our beliefs and 
personal history. Sometimes these efforts are correct. Other times they are inaccurate or distorted. This process is called filtering because of how 
our experience is altered. Some people are described as looking at the world through rose-colored glasses meaning they filter their experience by 
taking the most optimistic view of situations.</p>

<p>The effects of filtering are most profound in on our options and judgments about other people and situations. Individuals involved in the same group 
social interaction can report very different interpretations of what just occurred. A common saying illustrating how views can differ is some see 
the glass of water as half empty and others see it as half full. Filtering can take the form of an internal narrative or thought pattern where the 
focus of attention over emphasizes some characteristics while minimizing others.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the movie The Matrix (1999) the scene What is Real? has the main character named Neo connected to a computer simulation with a terminal jack in the back of his head. Once in the simulation Neo questions the nature of his reality. The discussion puts forth a model of human perception where energy signals such as light, sound, heat, and chemicals impinge on the sensory receptors in the human body. The receptors react sending impulses through the nervous system to the brain. The brain interprets these impulses constructing a mental model creating an individual’s experience of the world around them as what they see, hear, feel, smell, and taste. Our sensory system only samples a small amount of the energy fields and chemical molecules present in the environment directly around us. Our brains interpolate to fill any gaps where data is missing. The sensory processing system can be thought of as our input from the physical world we live in.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-real.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-real.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Feelings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/feelings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feelings" /><published>2022-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feelings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/feelings/"><![CDATA[<p>Feelings are very important. Emotional Intelligence (EI) has identified five characteristics as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Self Awareness</li>
  <li>Empathy</li>
  <li>Motivation</li>
  <li>Self Regulation</li>
  <li>Social Skills</li>
</ol>

<p>Developing these areas is considered essential for personal growth and successful social interaction. EI is “the ability to identify and manage
 one’s own emotions, as well as the emotions of others.” (“Emotional Intelligence,” 2020) The very word emotion denotes what moves a person to take 
 action. The individual is best positioned to access and know their our feelings and emotions.</p>

<p>Using your emotions to reason or think misuses this key human faculty. Expressing your desires and wants is appropriately centered around one’s 
feelings. Saying a thing is true because it feels right is nonsense. Developing both emotional and reasoning skills along with applying those skills 
appropriately cultivate a well-balanced mind.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<p>Emotional Intelligence. (2020). Retrieved August 7, 2022, from Psychology Today website: 
<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/emotional-intelligence">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/emotional-intelligence</a></p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Feelings are very important. Emotional Intelligence (EI) has identified five characteristics as follows:]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/27/Emotions_according_to_the_Atlas_of_Personality%2C_Emotion_and_Behaviour.svg/256px-Emotions_according_to_the_Atlas_of_Personality%2C_Emotion_and_Behaviour.svg.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/27/Emotions_according_to_the_Atlas_of_Personality%2C_Emotion_and_Behaviour.svg/256px-Emotions_according_to_the_Atlas_of_Personality%2C_Emotion_and_Behaviour.svg.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Importance of Errors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-importance-of-errors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Importance of Errors" /><published>2022-07-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-importance-of-errors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-importance-of-errors/"><![CDATA[<p>People often believe if errors and mistakes didn’t occur their lives would be better and the world would be a better place to live. 
Errors are important and their essential nature is often overlooked. The discovery of penicillin occurred when mold contaminated samples 
in an experiment killing the bacteria being grown in Petri dishes.</p>

<p>The role of errors goes far beyond examples when beneficial results occur because of a mistake. The very essence of evolution and thus the key 
processes of life itself depend on errors. The copying of genetic material and reproduction happen imperfectly. Mutations are often 
but not always dysfunctional. Some of these errors create superior capabilities for organisms enhancing their survival. 
The vast web of life came about through what we usually perceive as errors and mistakes.</p>

<p>Creativity itself is a process where novel results and outcomes occur. By this definition, mistakes and errors are extremely creative. 
Often yielding results no one imagined or intended. Without errors, most of what we value and hold dear would not exist.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[People often believe if errors and mistakes didn’t occur their lives would be better and the world would be a better place to live. Errors are important and their essential nature is often overlooked. The discovery of penicillin occurred when mold contaminated samples in an experiment killing the bacteria being grown in Petri dishes.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/creativity.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/creativity.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Knowledge and does it matter?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Knowledge and does it matter?" /><published>2022-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/what-is-knowledge/"><![CDATA[<p>Some think knowledge is a belief which is always true. They might say, “I know the sun will come up tomorrow.” 
But, such a statement would prove false in the aftermath of a supernova. We can overcome this difficulty 
by eliminating the prediction and focusing on the present,
saying instead, “The sun came up today.” But did the speaker directly observe the sunrise? 
Or did they figure because the sun is in the sky it must have risen. 
What about days where it is light out, but clouds obscure the sun from view. We assume the sun is behind the clouds without actually seeing it.</p>

<p>Even when the statement is narrowed to the sun came up this morning, and I know this because I saw it rise, 
many other questions such as where you where located come 
into play. Is there a sunrise at the North pole? Requiring all knowledge to be the result of personal experience is very limiting. 
Moreover, studies have shown eyewitness accounts are often incorrect or misremembered. 
These findings can shake a persons faith in anyones ability to know anything.</p>

<p>This kind of dialog is what often irritates new students of philosophy. The seemingly endless questioning and doubting 
lead them to wonder why anyone should care about epistemology?</p>

<p>Rather than insist a belief must be universally true, we look at what is a reasonable justification. 
Things like “the sun will come up tomorrow” are common to human experience. 
Often referred to as common knowledge, such statements require little effort to convince others of their accuracy.</p>

<p>The problem of requiring knowledge to be always true extends to science. Newtonian mechanics made way for the theory of relativity. 
Yet today Newton’s theory is still taught as knowledge with the caveat that it works except in unusual situations 
such as moving very close to the speed of light. Relativity covers the extreme 
cases, but predicts the same outcomes as Newtonian mechanics for the usual conditions encountered.</p>

<p>Science uses a systematic approach to test validity. Repeatable experiments with measurements and 
objective observations are relied upon by a community of 
practitioners searching to understand phenomenon. Results are analyzed and 
the conclusions questioned and debated. Ultimately, scientists become convinced and accept 
the validity of the findings. This process like most involving people is a bit chaotic. 
Egos can challenged and tested. Mistakes and errors do occur while participants 
struggle and hope optimistically the truth will ultimately prevail.</p>

<p>For us at Research on Knowing, the key question is what evidence justifies holding that a belief is valid.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some think knowledge is a belief which is always true. They might say, “I know the sun will come up tomorrow.” But, such a statement would prove false in the aftermath of a supernova. We can overcome this difficulty by eliminating the prediction and focusing on the present, saying instead, “The sun came up today.” But did the speaker directly observe the sunrise? Or did they figure because the sun is in the sky it must have risen. What about days where it is light out, but clouds obscure the sun from view. We assume the sun is behind the clouds without actually seeing it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/bf/James-lee-BMO1SzQHWRs-unsplash.jpg/512px-James-lee-BMO1SzQHWRs-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/bf/James-lee-BMO1SzQHWRs-unsplash.jpg/512px-James-lee-BMO1SzQHWRs-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to On Knowing!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to On Knowing!" /><published>2022-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-on-knowing/"><![CDATA[<p>On Knowing is the blog for <a href="https://www.researchonknowing.com/">Research on Knowing LLC</a>. Here you will find articles posted exploring 
the practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.</p>

<p>Epistemology within Philosophy is “the theory of knowledge, especially with regard to its methods, validity, and scope. 
Epistemology is the investigation of what distinguishes justified belief from opinion.” (OxfordLanguages) 
Make sure to read the theory articles first for a basic foundation on our philosophy of knowledge.
Other posts will expand on this foundation diving deeper into the details.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, various other Research on Knowing projects apply our philosophy of knowledge. We at Research on Knowing believe the practical 
application of epistemology can open our eyes and change our point of view. 
The invention of the telescope changed humanities ideas and understanding of the stars and planets. 
The microscope made visible an unimagined world within a drop of water. 
These are examples of how making visible what was previously hidden has revolutionized our knowledge. 
Computers and software have expanded our knowledge by revealing unseen truths. 
Research on Knowing employs these kinds of changes in viewpoint to explore how we learn, understand and create things.</p>

<p>Thank you for joining us on this journey. We hope your discovers here at On Knowing will be enlightening.</p>]]></content><author><name>jamie</name></author><category term="OnKnowing" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Knowing is the blog for Research on Knowing LLC. Here you will find articles posted exploring the practical application of epistemology to advance how we learn, understand and create things.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Steinkauzflug.jpg/512px-Steinkauzflug.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Steinkauzflug.jpg/512px-Steinkauzflug.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>